A Guide to the Burke Family Papers, 1800-1873
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Burke Family Papers, 1800-1873
The Library of Virginia
22870
41 leaves, negative photostats
Burke Family
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Lent for copying, 16 June 1948, by George H. S. King, Fredericksburg, Virginia.
Biographical Information
George Washington Burke (24 April 1823-28 July 1896) was a prosperous farmer in Caroline County, Virginia. Burke served in the 9th Virginia Cavalry in 1861-1862. He married three times. He married first, Dorthea B. Washington (d. by 1850) 2 July 1844, and they had at least one son. He married second, Eliza Taliaferro (1833-by 1882). and they had at least 3 children. He married third, Bettie DeJarnette (1851-1930) 30 October 1882. Thomas H. Burke (1845-1885[?]) attended Hanover Academy in Hanover County, Virginia. When the Civil War began, he served in the 9th Virginia Cavalry, then transferred to the 4th Virginia Cavalry, and was paroled at Appomattox Court House. After the Civil War, he studied law at the University of Virginia, then practiced in Paducah, Kentucky, and San Francisco, California. He died in San Francisco about 1885.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1800-1873, of the Burke family of Caroline County, Virginia, consisting of letters, 1850-1861, from family and friends discussing personal news and Texas during the early days of the Civil War; and letters, 1860-1873, from Thomas Henry Burke (1845-1885?) discussing his education at Hanover Academy, Virginia and secession; his education at the University of Virginia law school, and his establishment of a legal practice in San Francisco, California. Papers also include wills, 1800-1857, of Holt Richeson (d. 1800) of King William County, Virginia, Thomas Henry Burke (d. 1829) of Caroline County, and Elliott DeJarnette (1788-1857) of Spotsylvania County, Virginia; a writ against the estate of Festus Dickinson (ca. 1795-1845); certificate of exemption for George W. Burke from military duty; a receipt from Fauquier White Sulphur Springs; and an affidavit concerning Thomas H. Burke, his health and inability to return to military duty.
Contents List
- Will, dated 14 March 1800 and recorded 27 October 1800, of Holt Richeson (d. 1800) of King William County, Virginia.
- Will, dated 23 December 1823 and recorded 8 June 1829, of Thomas Henry Burke (d. 1829) of Caroline County, Virginia.
- Writ, 8 April 1846, issued by the circuit superior court of law and chancery against the estate of Festus Dickinson (ca. 1795-1845) to fulfill the order favoring Wesley Wright (1799-1879).
- Letter, 1 October 1850, from John W. Burke (b. 1825) of Alexandria, Virginia, to George Washington Burke (1823-1896) of Caroline County discussing personal news.
- Letter, 3 March 1853, from Courtes B. Sutton of Red River County, Texas, to George W. Burke containing personal news.
- Letter, 26 March 1853, from Courtes B. Sutton of Red River County, Texas, to George W. Burke containing personal news.
- Will, 20 July 1857 with a codicil dated 31 July 1857, of Elliott DeJarnette (1788-1857) of Spotsylvania County, Virginia.
- Certificate, 186[?], of exemption of George W. Burke from military duty signed by Captain Henry Hortensius George (1824-1902) of the Caroline Light Dragoons, 30th Cavalry Regiment.
- Letter, 2 April 1860, from Courtes B. Sutton to George W. Burke consisting of personal news.
- Letter, 24 June 1860, from Thomas Henry Burke (1845-1885[?]), attending Hanover Academy, to George W. Burke concerning his education and studies.
- Receipt, 24 August 1860, from Fauquier White Sulphur Springs, Fauquier, Virginia.
- Letter, 12 January 1861, from Thomas H. Burke to George W. Burke concerning South Carolina's seceding from the Union and the course of action Virginia should take.
- Letter, 24 June 1861, from Courtes B. Sutton to George W. Burke discussing events in Texas during the first months of the Civil War.
- Affidavit, 19 July 1862, of Dr. H. W. Davis concerning the inability of Thomas H. Burke to rejoin the 9th Virginia Cavalry due to his health.
- Letter, 19 April 1863, from Thomas H. Burke to George W. Burke detailing movements of his unit.
- Letter, 12 February 1867, from Thomas H. Burke at the University of Virginia to George W. Burke discussing his law studies.
- Letter, 10 May 1873, from Thomas H. Burke, San Francisco, California, to George W. Burke commenting on his move from Kentucky to San Fransisco and establishment of his law practice.
- Letter, no date, from Thomas H. Burke while attending Hanover Academy to George W. Burke containing personal news.
- Letter, no date, from Thomas H. Burke at Headquarters, Lee's Cavalry Brigade, to George W. Burke sending news about his unit.